Finding Aid for the Ruth Eleanor McKee Papers, 1905-1972
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Ruth Eleanor McKee Papers,
1905-1972
1151
McKee, Ruth Eleanor, 1903-
11 boxes (5.5 linear ft.) 1 oversize box
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Ruth Eleanor McKee (1903- ) spent ten years at the Library of Hawaii publishing poetry in small magazines and published her first novel on the history of Hawaii in 1934. While working as a historian for the War Relocation Authority (WRA) she wrote 3 monographs. In 1951 she began working for the United States Department of State and was appointed United States Consul at Tokyo in 1958. The collection consists of manuscripts, correspondence, and research materials related to Ruth E. McKee's work as a novelist, poet, United States Foreign Service officer, and writer for the War Relocation Authority (WRA). McKee's research for the WRA focused on Japanese American evacuation and internment during World War II.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Additional Physical Form Available
A copy of the original version of this online finding aid is available at the UCLA Department of Special Collections for in-house consultation and may be obtained for a fee. Please contact:
Public Services Division
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Room A1713, Charles E. Young Research Library
Box 951575
Los Angeles, CA 90095-1575
Telephone: 310/825-4988 (10:00 a.m. - 4:45 p.m., Pacific Time)
Email: spec-coll@library.ucla.edu
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret Ringnalda, 1975 and 1984.
Funding
This online finding aid has been funded in part by a grant from the Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA).
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 2221408
Biography
McKee was born in 1903 and grew up in Ventura County, California; BA, University of California, Southern Branch (later University of California, Los Angeles), 1926; spent ten years at the Library of Hawaii, publishing poetry in small magazines; published first novel on the history of Hawaii, 1934; wrote 5 subsequent novels; moved to Sonoma County, California, 1936; wrote 3 monographs while working as a historian for the War Relocation Authority (WRA); began working for the United States Department of State, 1951; appointed United States Consul at Tokyo, 1958; retired to Cape Cod, 1963.
Additional Biographical Narrative
Ruth Eleanor McKee (1903-) was a poet and novelist, a historian for the War Relocation Authority (WRA) and an officer in the U.S. Foreign Service. Her childhood was spent in Ventura County, California. She later wrote that it was this environment of isolation which caused her to begin reading and writing at an early age. Her first writings were journals and poems. At the age of 14 she took her father's car and a revolver and ran away to Los Angeles, seeking local color for a novel. She was found three days later, employed as a cook.
She received a Bachelor of Arts from the Southern Branch of the University of California in 1926. That same year she had enough money for a one-way ticket to Honolulu, and with Kathryn MacFarlane, also a writer, she began a new life in Hawaii.
She remained there for ten years, working at the Library of Hawaii. During this time she published poems in the small magazines of the day, such as Voices and Lyric West. Typescripts of her poems are here in the papers, as well as copies of some of the publications. She contributed dozens of book reviews to the Honolulu Star-Bulletin, signing herself R.E.M. In 1934 Doubleday in New York and John Lane in London published her first novel, The Lord's Anointed. Still considered one of the best fictions to treat the history of Hawaii, it received good reviews and sold well. She published five more novels.
In 1927 she had married a lieutenant in the Army Air Corps, Darr Alkire. She was divorced the following year and assumed custody of her son Michael. They left Hawaii for California in early 1936 to live in the Redwoods in Sonoma County. There she wrote her last published novels, all of them successful critically and financially. The most successful was Christopher Strange, a novel of California from Gold Rush days through the turn of the century, including the development of Palm Springs.
She wrote three significant monographs while working as historian for the WRA. These monographs were summaries and analyses after the fact. Research materials for this writing are in part here in the papers. She also began novels about Japanese Americans, but these were not published. They exist here in manuscript, and are perhaps of some value in recreating the lives of those people whom she observed and with whom she had great empathy.
Michael was killed in a plane crash in 1950. In 1951 she began working for the Department of State, ghostwriting articles, primarily about Germany. In 1958 she was appointed United States Consul at Tokyo, for Tokyo, by President Eisenhower. She hoped to use this experience to further her knowledge about Japan and Japanese Americans. She retired from the Foreign Service in 1963 and moved to a house she had built in West Chatham, Massachussetts, on Cape Cod, where she lived until her death.
The papers are the gift of her literary executrix, Mrs. Margaret Ringnalda.
by Dan Luckenbill, May 1975
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts, correspondence, and research materials related to Ruth E. McKee's work as a novelist, poet, United States Foreign Service officer, and writer for the War Relocation Authority (WRA). McKee's research for the WRA focused on Japanese American evacuation and internment during World War II.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Biographical and correspondence (Boxes 1-4).
Journals and diary (Boxes 5-6).
Poetry, prose fiction, non-fiction prose (Box 7).
Published novels (Box 8).
Unpublished novels (Box 9).
Writings for War Relocation Authority (Box 10).
Writings for U.S. Signal Corps, U.S. Dept. of State, and manuscripts by other writers (Box 11).
Certificates and book review clippings (Oversize Box 12).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
McKee, Ruth Eleanor, 1903- .; United States. War Relocation Authority.; United States. Army. Signal Corps.; Authors, American--20th century--Archival resources.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945--Research.
Container List
- Biographical (Box [1])
  - Autobiography. 1946., 6 leaves. Typescript, with holograph notes. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Written in the fall of 1946 for some application for a writing fellowship.
  - Photos of Ruth Eleanor McKee. 1905, 1907, 1918, 1930, 1952, 1963 and n.d., 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, giving general information about Ruth Eleanor McKee. 1936, 1938 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diplomas, etc., See also: Oversize Box 12. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 8th grade. 1916.
    - Manual Arts High School. 1920.
    - Teacher's credential, Southern Branch of the University of California. 1923.
    - Credential, State Board of Education. 1923.
    - Master of Arts, University of Hawaii. 1930.
    - Certificate from School of Librarianship, University of California at Berkeley. 1939.
  - Marriage and divorce. Marriage certificate, Honolulu. 1927. Decree of divorce, Territory of Hawaii. 1928. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Michael Alkire.
    - Letters to Michael Alkire. 1944. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Michael Alkire to Ruth Eleanor McKee. 1945-46 and 1950. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Photos. n.d., 6 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Armed services records. 1945-48, 1950 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Written numerology. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Clippings. ca. 1950. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Legal items after his death. 1950. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters, expressing sympathy to Ruth E. McKee. September-October 1950 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diplomatic passport. 1958. Travel documents. 1960 and 1963. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Travel vouchers. 1963. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Retirement from foreign service. Certificate and letter. 1963. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Consular service, Japan. Ephemera, etc. collected 1958-63., See also: Oversize Box 12. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - House at Harding Shores, West Chatham, Massachusetts. Correspondence, legal items, specifications and drawings. September 1957-October 1963. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings concerning friends of Ruth Eleanor McKee: (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Kathryn MacFarlane Thompson. 1936-38, 1946 and n.d.
    - Elmire Goldthwaite. 1941.
    - Julia Montgomery. 1957.
- Correspondence (Box [1-4])
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box [1])
    - Miscellaneous correspondence. 1920, 1931, 1935, 1943, 1950-51, 1957 and 1965., Includes letter from Lily Bess Campbell. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - With agents, editors and publishers. 1928-1973., 21 items. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters from Kathryn MacFarlane Thompson. 1947 and 1958. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letters to Margaret Ringnalda from Kathryn MacFarlane Thompson. 1934-35 and 1940. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Enclosures to the Ringnalda correspondence. 1942-43 and 1953. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters from Ruth Eleanor McKee to Margaret Ringnalda (Box [2-4])
    - 1934 and 1937-41. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1942-44. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1945. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1946. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1947. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1948. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1949. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1950. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1951. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1952. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1953. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1954. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1955. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1956. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1957 (1 item) and 1958. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1959. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1960-61. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1962. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1963. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Ruth Eleanor McKee to Eleanor Grahl (Box [4])
    - 1966-68. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1969-72. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Margaret Ringnalda to Ruth Eleanor McKee, [Addition, 1985] (Box [4])
    - ca. 1931-32, 1940, 1943-45, 1947 and 1949., Most have news about C.F. McIntyre. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Journals (Box [5-6])
  Of a diary nature, although many contain drafts of poems. All are in composition books of varying sizes.
  - 1913-1951 (inclusive dates)., The following headings were given by the literary executrix: (Box 5)
    - Tulare, Los Angeles, Ventura. 1913-17.
    - UCLA-Hawaii. 1924-31.
    - Berkeley, Los Angeles. 1938-39.
    - Healdsburg, Washington, D.C. 1940-48.
    - Washington, D.C. 1948-51.
  - 1951-1971 (inclusive dates)., 12 items of a diary nature. (Box 6)
  - 1930-1935 (inclusive dates)., 4 items with general notes on readings, etc. (Box 6)
- Manuscripts and Publications Materials (Box [7-11])
  - Poetry (Box [7])
    - Typescripts of poems. ca. 1919-50., 48 titles. 67 leaves. (Box 7, Folder 1)
      All of these appear to be copies, with very little correction of text. Many have holograph notes giving place of publication or circumstances of their composition.
    - Publications with poems by Ruth Eleanor McKee. 1928[?] and 1931-33., 9 items. (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Note: copies of Lyric West have been removed and added to the Department's holdings.
    - Poems: Ruth Eleanor McKee, n.p. n.d., [19]pp. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Keepsake printed by Margaret Ringnalda for the friends of Ruth Eleanor McKee.
    - [Hawthorne: a study of the modifications which took place in his attitude toward sin]. No author given. n.d., ca. 50 leaves. Typescript. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Has note by Ruth Eleanor McKee: Research Nathaniel Hawthorne.
  - Prose Fiction - [Unpublished (?)] (Box [7])
    - Juvenilia., One story, with note by Ruth Eleanor McKee: As far as I can recall I wrote this at about 18, maybe 19. I submitted it to The Smart Set! (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Stories, Ruth Eleanor McKee, The Library of Hawaii, Honolulu, T.H., 5 items. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Stories, Healdsburg., 4 items. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Stories written under pseudonyms., 6 items. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Unfinished manuscripts., 6 items. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Unfinished manuscripts. 1965-67., 1 item (2 copies). (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Non-Fiction Prose (Box [7])
    - Publication about Library of Hawaii. Library Journal. 1932. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Publication about Library of Hawaii. Honolulu Star-Bulletin. 1933. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - A word about American poetry. In The New Americans. 1933. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Notes for lecture [?]. n.d., 9 leaves. Typescript. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - [Review of novel by Rose Macaulay]. n.d., 1p. Typescript. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Clippings of book reviews from Honolulu Star-Bulletin written by Ruth Eleanor McKee when working at the Library of Hawaii. ca. 1930-33., See also: Oversize Box 12. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Published Novels (Box [8])
    - Research notes about Hawaii. Possibly for The Lord's Anointed or After a Hundred Years. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - The Lord's Anointed.
      - Correspondence. 1934 and n.d. (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Dust jackets from various printings. (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Clippings of reviews. 1934-35 and n.d. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - After a Hundred Years.
      - Correspondence, publishing agreement. 1935. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Clippings of reviews. 1935. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Under One Roof.
      - Carbon typescript. 1936 [?]., 208 leaves. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Publishing agreement. 1936. (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Dust jacket. (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Clippings of reviews. 1936. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Three Daughters.
      - Notes, in composition book. Healdsburg. 1938 [?]. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence. 1938. (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Clippings of reviews. 1938. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Christopher Strange.
      - Holograph notes in composition book. ca. 1941. (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence. ca. 1941. (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Publication announcement. 1941. (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - Dust jacket and photograph of dust jacket painting. (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Clippings of reviews. 1941. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Storm Point. Dust jacket. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Unpublished Novels (Box [9])
    - Follow the birds: a story of the hop harvest. n.d., 128 leaves. Carbon typescript. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Scattered notes for Japanese-American novel. In composition book. ca. 1957. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - The refuge. n.d., 386 leaves. Typescript with some holograph corrections.; f.1 of 2: leaves 1-167. (Box 9, Folder 3)
      First book of projected Japanese American novel for which Ruth E. McKee kept the WRA materials and asked for Embassy duty in Japan.
    - The refuge. n.d., f.2 of 2: leaves 168-386. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - In the beginning. n.d., 3 leaves. Typescript with some holograph corrections. (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Possible prologue to The refuge [?]
    - Portrait of an American. n.d., 154 leaves. Typescript with some holograph corrections. (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Beginning of second book in Japanese American saga.
  - Writings for the War Relocation Authority (WRA) (Box [10])
    - Holograph notes concerning relocation centers, etc. ca. 1942-46., In 2 composition books. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Grace Nichols Pearson. March 1943-July 1946 and n.d., Note by Ruth Eleanor McKee: Special WRA references in letters. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence having to do with WRA, Japanese-Americans, etc. 1945 and n.d. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Press releases, etc. from Tule Lake Segregation Center. Primarily concerning removal of internees because of violence in the center. June-July and December 1944 and n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Department of the Interior. 1945., Mimeographed items. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - [History of Evacuation and WRA Program] by Ruth E. McKee. n.d., 246 leaves. Carbon typescript with some holograph corrections. (Box 10, Folder 6)
      With note by Ruth Eleanor McKee: Carbon of edited version was submitted to Interior - to Miss Sylvia Altman. This was not censored.
    - California and Her Less Favored Minorities: a Study of the Evacuation of Persons of Japanese Ancestry from the Pacific Coast, War Relocation Authority. April 1944., 27, iv [4] leaves. Mimeograph. (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Prepared by Ruth E. McKee, WRA historian.
    - The Wartime Handling of Evacuee Property. United States Department of the Interior, War Relocation Authority. Washington, D.C., U.S. Government Printing Office. 1946., 113pp. Mimeograph. (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Note on cover by Ruth Eleanor McKee: This is just tossed in gratis, the most exacting and tedious of my writing assignments for WRA - I have a more entertaining one but have only one copy.
    - Wartime Exile: the Exclusion of the Japanese Americans from the West Coast. Washington, D.C., U.S. Government Printing Office for United States Department of the Interior, War Relocation Authority. 1946., 167pp. (Box 10, Folder 9)
      This report prepared by Ruth E. McKee.
    - The Latest Word: WRA Reports Alumni Association. News Bulletin. (Box 10, Folder 10)
      no.1 (November 1945)
      no.2 (January 1946)
      no.3 (April 1946)
      no.4 (June 1946)
      no.5 (August 1946)
      no.9 (July 12, 1949)
      Also, final issue Ave Atque Vale (n.d.).
    - Correspondence of Earl M. Finch with Frank Cross, WRA, concerning Japanese American servicemen. June 1944. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Clippings concerning Japanese Americans. 1941-42, 1945-46, 1948, 1950 and n.d. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - WRA. Miscellaneous printed materials. ca. 1942-45. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Writings for the United States Signal Corps (Box [11])
    - The Signal Corps' Bird of War. n.d., 48 leaves. Typescript with some holograph corrections. Another copy. Carbon typescript. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Signal Corps technical information letter. August 1945., 40pp. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Terrett, Dulany. [Signal Corps report]. ca. 1949., 11 leaves. Mimeograph. (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Note by Ruth Eleanor McKee: Re-hash of Ruth McKee's material by her superior Terrett in Pentagon - great conflict and indignation on her part.
    - Research material [?] Correspondence, memoranda, etc. concerning Roberts death ray. 1939-43., Some items bear the note: copy for Miss McKee. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Research material [?] Outlines of Signal Corps topics. 1945., ca. 60 leaves. Carbon typescripts. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Writings for the Department of State (Box [11])
    - Publications containing articles ghostwritten by Ruth Eleanor McKee. 1951-53., 7 items. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Includes one publication with authorship not annotated by Ruth Eleanor McKee.
    - Department of State publications about Japan and Germany. 1955 and 1957. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Clipping about writing of State Department pamphlets. 1957. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous printed and mimeographed items collected by Ruth Eleanor McKee during her period of writing for the Signal Corps and State Department. ca. 1943-57. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Manuscripts by Other Writers (Box [11])
    - Thompson, Kathryn MacFarlane. Poems & fiction. ca. 1929-47., ca. 60 leaves. (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Some were written to Ruth Eleanor McKee and are annotated by her.
    - Rogers, Gene. My Friend Anna. n.d., 11 leaves. Typescript. (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Certificates and Book Review Clippings (Box [Oversize Box 12])
  - Bachelor of Arts Degree, Southern Branch of the University of California. 1926. (Box 12)
  - Certificates from the Department of State, with appointment as Foreign Service Officer, class four; secretary in the diplomatic service; and Consul of the United States. 20 July 1955., 4 items. (Box 12)
  - Certificate from the Department of State, appointment as Consul of the United States of America at Tokyo, Japan, for Tokyo. 28 July 1958. (Box 12)
  - Certificates in Japanese with seal of the Embassy of the United States of America, Tokyo. Also translation of October 1 document. 8 July and 1 October 1958., 2 items. (Box 12)
  - Clippings of book reviews by Ruth Eleanor McKee from Honolulu Star-Bulletin. ca. 1930-1933., Pasted on oversize scrapbook pages. (Box 12)
    No dates on items.
Items Removed from Collection
Copy of Healdsburg Enterprise,Wednesday, November 28, 1888. Miscellaneous American Newspapers (Collection 1661). Box 7.
Galley proofs of Christopher Morley's Mandarin in Manhattan. Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection (Collection 100). Box 136.
Copies of Lyric West. 1928[?] and 1931-33 have been removed and added to the Department's holdings.